hey guys and welcome back to another
video so if you clicked on this video
you're either a student who is looking
to get into consulting or you're a
professional who's currently working and
may be also interested in potentially
making a lateral move into Consulting in
the future for those of you who don't
know me my name is Matt and I'm a
current associate at BCG which is a
management consulting firm and today
we're going to go through a BCG round
two case interview and I'm going to show
you by walking you through step by step
how I would solve this case so hopefully
you can get a better idea of what to
look for in a case interview now before
we get into the case I do want to say
that for best results you should take
the time to attempt this case yourself
before watching my explanation and walk
through because that's really going to
help you think through the case and
really fully understand the context and
just overall learn how to do this case
better but if it's your first time or
maybe you're too intimidated to attempt
the case yourself then just keep
watching let's get right into it so the
case we're going to be doing today is
called styrofoam situation and the
prompt reads as follows your client is
the CEO of cupco a national supplier of
Starr from cups to restaurants while
profit has been steady she is worried
about the influx of Cheaper products
from China by a new competitor called
chalice and has called you in to give a
recommendation on how to ensure
continued
profitability now the first thing you
always want to do when the prompt is
being read to you is you want to take
quick notes on the situation and after
you take notes you want to ask at least
at least one or two clarifying questions
now the reason you want to ask
clarifying questions is not just for
your own understanding of the situation
but also because you want to demonstrate
to the interviewer that you are thinking
thoughtfully and that you are also
listening to them and so I'm going to
just quickly write down some notes on my
iPad to show you how I would do it so
again the client is cupco they make
styrofoam
cups
they are
profitable but there's a new
entrant
chalice they're a lowcost
competitor and they're from
China and so now I'm going to come up
with a few claring questions now there's
an unlimited amount of questions that
you could ask to clarify the situation
but I'm just going to come up with a few
for the purposes of this case so one
that I can think of right off the bat is
is
cupco only us-based
this is important because I want to
understand is there potential for them
to move into other countries or are they
only looking to compete in the US market
I also want to understand have
they tried
anything or is this the first time that
they're looking into this because if
they've tried something then maybe there
is some additional data that already
exists that would be helpful for us now
for the purposes of being thorough I'll
just come up with one more clarifying
question and that could be something
like just clarifying that they only
serve restaurants so do they only serve
restaurants
because it could be interesting to see
if there's potential for them to serve
other types of businesses that need
starfam
cups so the way I would present this to
the
interviewer is I would say okay great so
it sounds like our client is cupco
they're a us-based manufacturer of
starfam Cups and they're profitable
which is great but recently a newer
lower cost player chalice has come in
from China and now management is worried
about the threat of this new entrance
and so we've been brought in to really
assess the Potential Threat whether or
not this is a threat really and what
they can do in response to this and so a
couple clarifying questions that I just
had are you know is cupco only us-based
and then the interviewer might say uh
yes they're only us-based no plans to
expand
internationally okay great have they
tried anything already to mitigate this
threat or to address this or to look
into it uh no this is the reason why
they're hiring you um okay great do they
only serve restaurants or are there
other types of business business in
their customer base no right now they
only serve restaurants and there's no
plans to expand beyond that however
based on your recommendation things
could change cool and so then I would
say great can I just take 60 seconds to
structure my thoughts and the
interviewer will say yes and that's your
cue to kind of go ahead and start
thinking through a framework for this
case now because this is a competitive
business strategy case I for the
purposes of Simplicity today am going to
be using the business situation
framework from Victor Chen for those of
you who don't know what that is it
basically consists of four buckets now
the first bucket is going to be the
competition the second bucket is going
to be the
company the third bucket is going to be
the
customer and the fourth bucket is always
product and what you would after this is
you would then look into at least two or
three key questions for each of these
buckets basically two or three key
questions that you would want to learn a
little bit more about in order to get a
better understanding of the situation so
I'm just going to write a few down
here and I'll explain them after I'm
done okay great so now I'm going to walk
you through my framework and I'll
pretend that I'm interviewing so if I
was the interviewer I would say okay
great so broadly speaking there are four
buckets that I would want to dig a
little bit deeper into to better
understand the situation the first is
going to be the competition the second
is going to be the company itself the
third is going to be the customer and
the fourth is going to be understanding
the product itself now I'll talk a
little bit more about each of these
buckets so going back to the first
bucket competition here I want to
understand two things first is the
market how large is this Market is it
growing is it shrinking is it a massive
Market is a very small Market also want
to understand who the competitors are is
this a market that is highly fragmented
which means there's many many tiny
players or is it a market that's
dominated by a few very large
competitors which would make it very
difficult for a new entrance to play
moving to the second bucket the company
itself here I just want to better
understand where are the company's key
differentiators their key strengths lie
what are they really good at is it their
supply chain is it their R&D their
design team is it their ability to have
really strong relationships with vendors
and also what are their financials now
we understand that the company is
currently profitable but is there
anything more important here to consider
that would influence their ability to
potentially say lower prices to match
their competitors thirdly with the
customer bucket here I really want to
understand what do customers care about
what are their preferences do they
desire One S sort of cup over another
because maybe there's something about
our cup that is hopefully better than
the cheaper lower cost competitors
cup also what is their price elasticity
because if we're going to try and lower
prices how is that going to influence
the demand for our product conversely if
we increase our prices how many of our
customers will stop buying from
us finally with a product bucket here I
want to understand the unit economics
know the unit price unit cost unit
profit for both our competitor chalice
and cupco to understand what our unit
profitability looks like as well as any
potential differentiators about our
product is this a relatively
commoditized product meaning that anyone
can produce it and so there's very
little differentiation or is it a
product where you can really
differentiate and justify charging a
higher price so that's how I would walk
the interviewer through my framework now
before we keep going I want to note that
the business situation framework is a
very helpful framework especially if you
are a
because it gives you a set of structured
buckets and areas that will help solve
like 90% of cases now one caveat is that
it only works with business strategy
situations so for example you can't use
this framework if you are being given a
case about like nonprofits or some topic
that is completely unrelated to business
and competitive strategy also you
shouldn't try to anchor on this
framework for every single case because
there are going to be certain cases that
will require you to adapt this framework
or use a completely different framework
to begin with but this is a good one for
those of you who are just learning and
don't really know where to start because
it's a very strong foundation so usually
from this point what happens is the
interviewer will either suggest that you
look into a certain area of the
framework or they will ask you where in
this framework you want to start first
now if the ladder is what happens then
you want to basically choose the bucket
in your framework that you feel most
compelled by that you think is going to
be most important fully understanding
that the goal here would be to go
through every single bucket in the
framework until you eventually hit the
key Insight that's going to drive your
recommendation so in this situation
let's just say that I am very interested
in understanding the unit economics of
the product like how much does it
actually cost each of these businesses
to produce a cup and what are they
charging for these cups right so I would
say okay well I want to understand the
product a little bit more do we have any
information related to either the unit
economics or you know the product itself
and fortunately for me there is some
data here in exhibit one we can take a
look I'll also write it down and we have
a table that's giving us the unit price
and unit costs for each of these
companies now the first thing you want
to do whenever you are given an exhibit
like this is you want to take maybe 5
Seconds to look at it and then you want
to start by giving your initial
reactions like literally talk out loud
to the interviewer even if you don't
know what the big Insight is yet you
want to talk out loud and give them your
reaction so they understand what's going
on in your mind and that's also much
better than just having an awkward
silence where you're just digesting the
data and trying to think of some like
super witty or super smart insightful
thing to say so what I might tell the
interviewer is okay great so it looks
like we have the unit price and unit
cost for cupco and chalice and right off
the bat I can see that the price for
cupco is 10 cents per unit whereas
chalice is only charging 7 cents per
unit um now that's not a surprise
because we knew that chalice was a lower
cost competitor but what's also
interesting is the cost structure
because it looks like cupco has $7 in
manufacturing or 7 cents rather in
manufacturing and shipping costs but
chalice incurs an additional 2 cents in
distribution cost per unit so actually
chalice is operating at a
loss
now immediately there should be alarm
Bells going off in your head you should
be wondering why this is the case right
why would a business
knowingly operate at a unit loss for
every unit that they're selling and
right off the bat the first thing that
comes to my mind at least is Market
entry and maybe they're trying to do
some sort of loss leader strategy where
they are deliberately charging a much
lower price than the existing
competition in order to gain a foothold
into the market now this definitely
isn't a sustainable strategy for them to
continue losing money but just thinking
through why this might be the case and
thinking aloud to your interviewer is
going to really help you do well on this
case another observation that you should
be thinking about is on the price side
what would happen if cupco lowers their
prices to match chalice right and we can
see right off the bat that this is not
really feasible because if they were to
lower their price to 7 cents per unit
then they would be making zero profit
and again we have to keep in mind the
whole case from the beginning is based
on how can we maintain profitability
while still establishing our competitive
position so making zero profit is not an
option now at this point you want to
stop and let the interviewer give you
their reaction to your findings and one
mistake I see a lot of students do is
they tend to Ramble On and On in a case
because they're nervous and they
sometimes when they don't know know what
the answer is they think that by talking
for a long time they'll eventually get
to the right answer but the problem here
is that the interviewer is often going
to give you very valuable feedback on
whether or not you're going in the right
direction or not and so if you don't
give them the chance to speak and just
redirect you then you're basically
shooting yourself in the foot and a lot
of interviewers they want you to succeed
and so you guys should really stop after
you give your general observation and
ask them like does this sound good to
you for example after you give your
framework or after you give your
analysis of a particular exhibit just
ask them does this sound good to you and
so they'll often give you some super
helpful feedback that'll either confirm
or disprove the direction that you're
headed in and that's going to help you
avoid awkward situations where you do a
ton of math or you do a ton of thinking
and you basically just go down the
completely wrong path of the case and
you don't even end up at the answer or
you end up at a completely incorrect
answer so always pause after each
section of the case and see what the
interviewer has to say so let's say that
in this case scenario they agree with me
but there's no further learnings from
this and so I go back to my framework
and I say okay I want to understand a
little bit more than the customer so you
know do we have any information on the
customer preferences or perhaps their
price elasticity and here the
interviewer would say yes we actually do
have Exhibit 2 here which is uh from a
prior Market study that we conducted
where we surveyed a bunch of our
customers and we learned about their
preferences and so right off the bat
again you want to react to this so how I
would do this is I would maybe say
something like okay well this is really
interesting it looks like based on my
initial read that service
reliability is by and
far the number one
criteria for
customers far beyond even things like
price and design and even better is is
the fact that we excel in service
reliability it looks like we have an
eight whereas chalice has a six on a
service reliability score and so this is
really really great news for us because
it means that we actually do have an
edge on our competitor on a dimension
that customers really do care
about so then from this point you want
to get the interview's reaction and what
they should do is they should recommend
that you move into the next phase of the
case which is a brainstorming portion
and the way that they would do this is
they would say something along the lines
of okay so then why don't we come up
with a few ideas for what cupco can do
in response to chalice now based on the
findings from today and so that's your
cue to really start the brainstorming
session and don't be afraid to take a
little bit of time what I've done in the
past is I've asked for 30 seconds to
think through a couple good ideas and
most people are completely fine with
that so don't feel the need to just
completely Jump Right In in uh
especially if you have nothing in your
mind at the moment and you really need
some time to really think through some
good
answers so I'm just going to do this now
out
loud and I'm just going to throw a few
ideas down
here okay great so now I'm just going to
walk you through a few ideas that have
come up with that I think would make
sense based on what we've learned today
so the first is really leaning into the
service strength that we have as a
business now some potential ways that we
could do this are something like
offering expedited shipping services
like two-day shipping if we don't do
that already and really leverage our
stronger supply chain and service
reliability to offer a superior customer
experience than our competitors can and
also really leaning in when it comes
comes to sales and marketing when we're
trying to acquire new customers really
demonstrating to them that hey look our
current customers are super satisfied
with our service reliability and
therefore we can offer that to you as
well and I think that could be a really
compelling value proposition to win new
customers a second idea that I had is we
could potentially lower price now yes
this would cut into profits but I'm not
suggesting that we lower prices to match
chalice instead if we lower price by a
smaller margin we might be able to
capture a greater share of the existing
Market finally we can also create longer
term contracts with our existing
customers now the reason why this is a
good idea and this is a little less
obvious is that if we are currently
doing very well with our current
customers then we might be able to
renegotiate our contracts with them so
that they're locked in for a longer
period of time maybe instead of 5 years
it's 7 years and so this is going to
provide a larger Mo because for 7 years
our customers aren't going to switch
over and go to the lower cost competitor
now one thing that I found is sometimes
interviewers will press you a little bit
more and they'll say anything else and
they'll try to get you to think really
hard about any additional ideas and so
don't panic if you get asked this but
just take a deep breath and really think
through any possible other ideas that
you can think of for this brainstorming
session but after this you move to the
last portion of the case which is going
to be the synthesis and now the way this
typically goes is the interviewer will
tell you
okay great so now let's imagine that the
CEO of cupco is down the hall and she's
walking towards the conference room
where you and your team are currently
working and in about 30 seconds she's
going to ask you to provide a
recommendation based on your findings
today how would you do that and so you
as the interviewer will then take about
30 seconds to come up with your
recommendation and there's a helpful
structure that I like to use whenever
I'm doing synthesis at the end of a case
the first is you know
context the second is
findings the third
is
recommendation the fourth is any
potential
risks and the fifth and final step is
potential next
steps and what I find is a lot of people
actually miss this last step here but if
you remember it it's a very good way to
differentiate yourself from the
competition and so I would take about 30
seconds to quickly review your notes and
really recall what the most important
findings were from the case before you
give this recommendation and an example
of how I might give this recommendation
is I would say great thanks for joining
us uh as you know we're currently
working on understanding the competitive
threat that chalice faces and today what
we've found is that our competitor
chalice is actually operating at a unit
loss for every unit that they're selling
whereas we are currently operating at a
profit which is great news uh
additionally another key finding from
our customer research was that customers
actually really value service
reliability over things like price or
design and we are fortunately very
strong on service reliability and we've
rated quite High uh much higher actually
than our competitors on this Dimension
and so given these findings what we
actually recommend is not doing any sort
of dramatic changes to the business but
rather exploring the potential for some
strategic moves like maybe lowering
prices by a slight amount or really
leaning into our service reliability
aspect when it comes to things like
sales and marketing or improving the
existing customer experience by offering
things like two-day shipping for example
now there are obviously some risks to
things like lowering price as that would
cut into our margins but as a potential
next step to better understand the
opportunity there we would really like
to do some additional customer research
on price elasticity and just further
explore the opportunity that lies within
leaning into our Logistics and our
service reliability strengths so that's
the case and that was just one way to
solve this case there are many other
correct ways to do this that's just how
I would have done it and I do want to
caveat that casing is really a skill
that you develop over time and the only
way to get better is to get more reps
but also to get good feedback from
people who know what they're doing and
so one of my biggest recommendations for
folks who are trying to develop their
casing skills is to case with friends
who are going to maybe internet
Consulting firms as well as casing with
existing Consultants that you have
networked with because that feedback is
really going to help you improve much
quicker but anyways if you found this
helpful make sure to hit the like And
subscribe button if you haven't already
and let me know in the comments below if
you have any questions or any
suggestions for future content and as
always I'll see you guys in the next one
peace